<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The embassage of Gods angell. By George Phillips</title>
            <author>Phillips, George, fl. 1597.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119180</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854387</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19805</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19805)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1554:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The embassage of Gods angell. By George Phillips</title>
                  <author>Phillips, George, fl. 1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[40] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by P. Short] for William Leake, and are to be solde at his shop in Paules Churchyarde at the signe of the Greyhound,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19805:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19805:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE EMBASSAGE OF Gods Angell.</p>
            <p>By George Phillips.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Malachi. cap. 3. verſe 1:</bibl>
               <p>Behold I will ſend my Meſsenger, and hee ſhall prepare the waie before me.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q xml:lang="lat">VERITAS TVA ET VSQVE AD NVBES</q>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed for William Leake, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Paules <hi>Churchyarde at the ſigne</hi> of the Greyhound. 1597.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19805:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19805:2"/>
            <head>The Embaſſage of <hi>Gods Angell.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>The Text is in the 5. Chapter of the Actes of the Apoſtles, the 20. verſe, &amp;c.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>20</hi> Go your way, and ſtand in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſpeake vnto the people, al the words of this life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>21</hi> So when they heard it, they entered into the Temple earlie in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and taught. And the chiefe prieſt came, &amp; they which were with him, and called the counſel together, &amp; al the elders of the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and ſent to the priſon, to cauſe them to be brought.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this ſpeech, wee muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the charge that was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the Apoſtles by the
<pb facs="tcp:19805:3"/>
Angell, and then how the Apoſtles executed the ſame. If wee conſider theſe thinges more particularlie: <hi>Goe your waie,</hi> is the incouragement that the Angell giueth to theſe apoſtles. <hi>Stand in the temple,</hi> admoniſheth to haue recourſe to the ordinarie place of teaching and hearing Gods word. <hi>Speake to the people,</hi> is Gods generall calling of al people to the knowledge of his truth.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2, 4</note> 
               <hi>Al the wordes of this life,</hi> doth ſignifie the ſubiect of our p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, viz. the Goſpell of Ieſu Chriſt which bringeth eternall life. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the angell calleth them the words of this life, hee hath relation to a life, which the apoſtles had preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their impriſonment, as in Actes the 4, and 12. verſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>Goe your waies.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>God ſaith of the wicked <hi>(viae meae, non ſunt viae veſtrae)</hi> My waies are not your waies. But here the Angel ſaith,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19805:3"/>
                  <hi>Go your waies. &amp;c.</hi> which was a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argument to theſe men that their authoritie was good. This muſt needs concerne vs of the Miniſtery verye neerelie,<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.1</note> that wee looke to our waies like Dauid, whether they bee ſuch as may incourage vs to proceed therein with a ſafe conſcience. For it is que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe, that becauſe the ſpirites of the Prophets are ſubiect to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14, 32</note> therefore ſaint <hi>Iohn</hi> vvilleth vs to trie the ſpirites, teaching vs like wiſe to knowe, vvhat ſpirits we muſt acknovvledge for fit leaders of Gods people.<note place="margin">Acts. 8.9</note> In <hi>Symon</hi> the Sorcerer was the ſpirite of inchauntment, wherewith he ſeduced the Samaritanes.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Iaſon</hi> the highe prieſt,<note place="margin">2 Maca. 4, 7</note> vvas the ſpirite of Briberie, whileſt hee corrupted (for that office of the prieſt hoode) <hi>Antiochus,</hi> vvho vvas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted againe by <hi>Menelaus.</hi> Our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt himſelfe telleth vs,<note place="margin">Iohn 10, 1</note> That euery one that commeth not in
<pb facs="tcp:19805:4"/>
by him the doore,<note place="margin">Neh. 13, 29</note> entereth in by a wrong way. And zealous <hi>Nehemia</hi> curſeth ſuch, as prophane polluters of Gods holie houſe, and defilers of his ſacred Prieſthood. And yet ſome haue taken this calling vppon them, before they coulde diſcharge it any better then <hi>Nicodemus</hi> could reaſon of regeneration:<note place="margin">Iohn 3, 9</note> and other haue gon the wrong waye to diſcharge theyr charge:<note place="margin">Ionas. 1, 3.</note> as <hi>Ionas</hi> fled to <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> when he ſhould haue gone to <hi>Niniue.</hi> And the Grandbiſhop of our ſoules,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 25</note> hath ordained this for a perpetuall and an infallible note of a true miniſter of Ieſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">Iohn 10, 9</note> 
                  <hi>By me if any man enter, he ſhall goe in and out, and ſhall find pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and ſhal bee ſafe:</hi> meaning, that they whoſe paſtures are bare, like the mountaine of <hi>Gilboa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.21</note> haue climed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the hurdles, or come in by ſome by-waie, and not by the right doore. And as no learning hath let them in, ſo a lawfull autoritie might ſhut them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19805:4"/>
out, that they might returne to theyr olde occupations againe, whereof they haue more skil,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4, 10</note> and wherin they haue moſt delight (as Demas in this Worlde) whoe haue taken ſo large a leape, as it is from the ſhop boord, to the ſheepefold. They only muſt build in Gods houſe, whom he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſo to doe, and inabled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as when he ſaid to the apoſtles:<note place="margin">Math. 28, 18 19</note> 
                  <hi>All power is giuen vnto me in heauen and in earth: Goe therefore and teache all Nations, &amp;c.</hi> for God euer indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them with a greater meaſure of his grace, then the common ſorte of his people: (As Iacob ſaid of his elder ſonne <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> when hee bleſſed him: <hi>moreouer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 40, 22</note> 
                  <hi>I giue to thee one portion aboue thy brethren, which I gate from the Amorites with my ſword &amp; bow</hi>) That the miniſter may be a leg to the lame, an eie to the blinde, a ſtaffe to the aged, a teacher of the ignoraunt, and a guide to the wandering: elſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19805:5"/>
how ſhall he lifte my feete out of the mire that is as deepely plunged in it as I am? What hope haue I to eſcape the pit, when my guide is as blinde as a beetle? How ſhall he vpholde and ſtrengthen my weakneſſe, who is an vnſtaid man himſelfe? how ſhal other be taught by him whom God himſelf vnder the perſon of <hi>Nicodemus</hi> repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued for his ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce long ſince?<note place="margin">Iohn 3, 10</note> Thus did the people wander in that maze of poperie, as in a midnight of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the daies paſt. But (bleſſed be God) we may now ſee hovve truelie Paule ſaid ſometimes to the ſaintes at <hi>Epheſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5, 8</note> 
                  <hi>ye were darknes, but nowe are you light in the Lord,</hi> meaning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when they were gentiles they walked igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantlie as they that were in darkenes, but it pleaſed God to giue them his ſonne, who is the true light to inligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten euery one that commeth into the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 1.9</note>Iohn the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> beeing asked
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19805:5"/>
of the prieſts &amp; Leuites, what he was,<note place="margin">Iohn 1.23</note> ſaide not <hi>I am a crier,</hi> but hee anſvve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: <hi>I am the voice of a crier.</hi> Manye haue taken the title of the Lords cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vpon them, whoſe voices haue ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom been imployed in preparing the pathes of the Lorde. Whoe (if they omitted their duety of ignorance) might learne of <hi>Eſay</hi> to inquire of the Lorde: <hi>What ſhall I crie?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 40.6</note> And they vvhich knovve it might imitate the ſame Prophetes example, who ſaide that <hi>For Sions ſake hee woulde not bee ſilent,</hi> that Iacob may knovve Gods iudgementes, and Iſrael his Lavves.<note place="margin">Rom. 10, 14 15</note> For hovve ſhall the people heare without a preacher, and hovv ſhall they preache except they bee ſent? Lorde, howe many were there poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed vvith dumbe Diuelles, vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ignoraunce was the reputed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Deuotion! but in this our ſoule ſauing knovvledge of Ieſus CHRISTES Goſpell, it hath
<pb facs="tcp:19805:6"/>
pleaſed him to open the mouthes of ſuch as ſoundlie teach vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to knowe the true God and Ieſus Chriſt, whom he hath ſent to ſaue vs, is eternal life. Wherfore we are as greatlie bound to praiſe God,<note place="margin">Marke 7.31</note> for opening y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouths of ſuch men, as thoſe Galileans who ſaide: <hi>He hath done all things well, he hath made the deafe to heare, and the dumbe to ſpeake.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chr. 13, 9</note> Bleſſed be God, the daies which <hi>Ahia</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet complai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned of, are worne out of date: whoe ſaid, We haue ſuch prieſts as the Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions that be Idolatrous round about vs, as though we ſhould ſacrifice with a bullock and ſeauen Rams, to them which are no Gods. Then coulde men bee contented to ſee and ſuffer Gods ſanctuary to bee a ſtable for the ignorant aſſe. Surely it argueth that men could bee contented to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fes wel, whatſoeuer they performed: and to haue all thinges well, ſo that it were not effected by their means. For
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19805:6"/>
had they regarded Gods true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then ſhould not a company of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy men, haue caried avvaie the churches reuenues for an olde ſong, as Baals prieſtes conſumed the kings coſt, for ſaying O Ball heare vs:<note place="margin">1 Reg. 18, 26</note> blind Prophets ſhuld not lead the blinded people (hand in hand) vnto hell, nor the Diuell lead captiue both the ſedu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers, and the ſeduced, as the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines ruled Samſon,<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.21</note> hauing cut off his haire, and bored out his eies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>And ſtand in the Temple.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>This is added, to prooue that God hath appointed a ſetled and certaine place, wherein he will haue his name called vpon of his people:<note place="margin">Deu. 12, 5, 6</note> and it hath beene ſo euer ſithence that Temple at Ieruſalem was firſt builded by king <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Reg. 6</note> As the Pſalmiſt ment when he ſaid: <hi>Thither the tribes go vp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 122, 4</note> 
                  <hi>euen the tribes of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> And it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that in diuers ages, there were
<pb facs="tcp:19805:7"/>
ordinary places of aſſemblie, as well to the ſacriledge committed with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols, as for the ſeruice of the true god. For as the vvoman of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her predeceſſors worſhipped vppon the mount of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 4, 20</note> and Chriſte ſaid, that Ieruſalem was the ordinary place where Iſraell ſhoulde worſhip:<note place="margin">2 Reg. 5.18</note> So <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> worſhipped in the houſe of <hi>Rymmon,</hi> and <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> ſometimes at <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Reg. 12</note> and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles at <hi>Dan.</hi> But it is ſaide heere vnto the Apoſtles, <hi>ſtand in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> for that the Chriſtian Religion being an open faced Religion, doeth likewiſe require a publike profeſſion. According as our Sauior Chriſt ſaid to the Diſciples,<note place="margin">Math. 10.27</note> 
                  <hi>Quod dico vobis in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebris, praedicate in luce.</hi> What I teach to you priuately, that preache you publikelie. For it is not enough, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſaint Paule, that your heart doeth beleeue vnto ſaluation,<note place="margin">Rom. 10, 10</note> but your mouth muſt alſo make confeſſion to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19805:7"/>
iuſtification. <hi>Ne coelico fallaci vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur numina cultu,</hi> leaſt all (like <hi>Saule</hi>) ſhoulde worſhippe God for a faſhion, and not of Deuotion.<note place="margin">Supra Math. cap. <hi>21, 12</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi> in his Morals vpon Chriſtes going into the Temple, ſo ſoon as he came into the City ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this true reformer of his church, had tvvo ſpeciall reſpectes therein. The firſt, to ſhewe that the negligence of the people doeth much ariſe of the careleſneſſe of the Paſtor, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not there ſo often as he ought. And therefore was it a part of Paules care to ſaie to the Coloſſians, <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhe Archippus to looke to his charge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Coloſ. 4.17</note>
               </p>
               <p>Next, to aduertiſe all higher po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, to procure the good of <hi>GODS</hi> houſe by all the lawfull meanes they may: and in this ſence <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaid, that <hi>Kinges ſhoulde bee nurcing fathers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 49, 23</note> 
                  <hi>and Queenes nurcing mothers vnto it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:19805:8"/>
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>And ſpeake vnto the people.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>As the Apoſtles mightie deliuerance out of the common priſon, was a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of <hi>Zorobabels</hi> concluſion,<note place="margin">1 Eſdr. 4, 41</note> viz. that trueth is ſtrongeſt: So this freſhe charge and newe commiſſion giuen to them, muſt teach vs, that we priſe not the worde of God by that eſtimation that men of ſinne do value it.<note place="margin">Math. 7, 6 Matt. 15.25</note> For as ſwine cannot prize pearles, ſo the crums of this foode, are ſought for by ſuch, as know what it is worth. When the Apoſtles aunſwered the counſel at Ieruſalem with,<note place="margin">Acts. 4, 19</note> 
                  <hi>Whether it is better to obey God or man, iudge you;</hi> their ſpeech hath relation to the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandement of God (wee ſee) as to a rule and compaſſe, whereby his ſhip the Church is ſafe conducted in the ſea of this world. For right ſo as God ſaid to Moſes:<note place="margin">Exod. 5, 40</note> See that thou makeſt the Arke, according to the patterne that I ſhewed thee on the Mounte:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19805:8"/>
In like maner, ought all the enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a Chriſtian life, to bee leuelled by the worde of Gods preſcription. Chriſt ſaith, that when the ſhepherd is ſtricken, the flocke flyeth &amp; is ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.<note place="margin">1 Reg. 22, 17</note> And ſo <hi>Micaia</hi> did prophecie againſt Ahab the wicked king of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. But Chriſt neuer ſaide: that the good ſhepheard doeth fly from the flocke, though himſelfe be ſtricken: but that he ventureth his own life,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10, 11</note> to ſaue theirs, as appeareth by theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, whoe ceaſe not to doe that which God commandeth, though it bee with daunger of life. As the two good midwiues of Egypt woulde not kill the infantes, becauſe GOD hath ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murder.</hi> It was ſaid to the ſinfull man in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Iohn 5, 14</note> 
                  <hi>Goe thy waie and ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing befal thee.</hi> But when the Apoſtles are inlarged by the Angel of the Lorde, they are bidden to doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine as they did before. Then this is
<pb facs="tcp:19805:9"/>
the cauſe vvhye GOD is ſo preſent a helpe in our troubles,<note place="margin">Pſal 46, 1 Pſal. 50, 15</note> in deliuering vs when wee call vppon him, euen that wee might magnifie him the more.<note place="margin">Acts. 4, 18</note> 
                  <hi>We charge you that you ſpeake no more in this name,</hi> ſaieth the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Ieruſalem to theſe Apoſtles: But I commaund you, that ye ſpeake the more in this name, ſayth the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Lorde (novve yee are at libertie.) Therefore is the zeale of GODS Saintes figured in the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing fire, vvhich might not goe out but muſt burne both daie and night (by the Leuiticall Lavve) and as our ſeruice of GOD muſt bee perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,<note place="margin">Leuit. 6, 13</note> ſo muſte it bee without feare or doubting.</p>
               <p>Shoulde ſuch a manne as I am fly?<note place="margin">Nehe. 6, 11</note> (ſaid <hi>Nehemiah.</hi>) If the husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhoulde waite vntill there vvere no vvinde,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.4</note> hee ſhoulde neuer ſovve. Or if hee woulde not reape, till there be no clouds that threaten rain,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19805:9"/>
he ſhoulde neuer haue harueſt while he liueth. In that theſe Apoſtles are commanded to ſpeake vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; occaſion is offered to ſaie ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of thoſe ſimples whereof gods catholike church is compound: viz. of the people. New Ieruſalem hadde twelue gates, not onely to ſignifie the xii. Tribes of Iſraell,<note place="margin">Apoc. 21.12.</note> but further to teach that GOD woulde chooſe his church from all parts of the worlde. And this is that which our ſauior ſaid long ſithence: <hi>I haue other ſheep which are not of this folde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 10, 16</note> 
                  <hi>them alſo muſte I bring, and they ſhal heare my voice, and there ſhal be one ſheepfold and one ſheep heard.</hi> Whereby he meant, that hee would be one day as common to the Gentiles (thorough the preaching of his goſpell) as then he was proper to the firſt elected Iewes. For S. Iohns viſion muſt bee effected (or elſe the ſcriptures are not fulfilled) he ſaieth: he ſaw an angell flying thorough the<note place="margin">Apoc. 14, 6</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19805:10"/>
middeſt of heauen, hauing an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting goſpell to preach to them that dwell on the earth, and to euery Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and kindred, and tongue, &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. So that howſoeuer that bee true, that the Iſraelites were the peculiar people of God, to whom only pertai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the promiſe, the adoption, &amp; the couenant of God (as ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) yet now God vouchſafing a new couenant,<note place="margin">Rom. 9, 4 Iere. 5, 31</note> hath comprehended all Nations therein,<note place="margin">Acts. 2, 39</note> as ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Vnto you is the promiſe made and vnto your ſeed, &amp; vnto all that are yet a farre off,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oſe. 2, 23</note> 
                  <hi>euen ſo manie as God will call.</hi> And as <hi>Oſe</hi> the Prophet ſaid: god calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his people who were not his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple heretofore, and they (novv) do cal him their God, whoſe God hee was not in times paſt: <hi>For we were as ſheep going aſtraie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2, 25</note> 
                  <hi>but nowe returned to the ſheepeheard and biſhop of our ſoules, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 10, 15</note> So that Saint <hi>Peters</hi> viſion being accompliſhed, that which God hath
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19805:10"/>
cleanſed, manne may not count it vncleane:<note place="margin">Actes 10, 28</note> for (novv) GOD hath ſhewed me that I ſhoulde not count any man polluted, or vncleane, ſaith hee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>All the wordes of this life.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>This doth ſubſcribe to the truth of him, whoe beeing the life it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Iohn 14, 6 Matth. 4, 3</note> ſaide ſometimes, that <hi>There is not one worde in the booke of God, but it hath his Emphaſis, or powerfull effect vnto eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> founde by his ovvne experience,<note place="margin">Rom. 1, 16</note> that the wordes of the Goſpell tende all to the ſauing of Faithfull beleeuers: ſo hee proteſteth to the Church of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus, that hee kept not backe anie part of the Counſell of GOD, that was fitte for theyr ſaluation,<note place="margin">Acts. 20, 20</note> but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto them all that Counſell of GOD. Yet we, who are the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, muſt ſaie like <hi>Ieremy</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet:
<pb facs="tcp:19805:11"/>
                  <hi>Thy words were found by mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 15, 16</note> 
                  <hi>and I did eate them, and thy worde was vnto mee the ioy and reioicing of my hart.</hi> Or as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 132.6</note> 
                  <hi>Loe wee heard of the ſame at Ephrata, and found it in the Wood.</hi> When we come to Gods houſe, wee muſt attende rather what is ſpoken, then who ſpeaketh, becauſe if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard who teacheth, we ſhall oft hear the ſucceſſors of the Scribes &amp; Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, who onlie would ſay well: and bicauſe they hold in <hi>capite</hi> (ſo long as they teach the truth) wee muſt heare them,<note place="margin">Matth. 23, 2</note> and hold with them in that. <hi>Ei parti fauendum eſt quae rectum ſentit in veritate.</hi> We muſt leane to that ſide, which relieth vpon the truth: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid Chriſt: <hi>Quod dicunt facite, You muſt doe as they ſaie.</hi> If you attend what they ſay, you ſhal find them like the Apoſtles, for they ſpeak vnto you all the words of this life. And it is not only the word of life, becauſe it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken as from the Author of life, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19805:11"/>
it tendeth to eternall life, but <hi>(quia creditur)</hi> becauſe it is beleeued. And therefore ſaieth Paule:<note place="margin">Rom. 1, 16</note> 
                  <hi>It is the power of God able to ſaue euery beleeuer</hi> And when Eſay ſaid,<note place="margin">Eſay 53, 1</note> 
                  <hi>Lord who belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth our preaching?</hi> hee meant, that the want of beliefe is want of life. The wordes of the Goſpell are alſo called the words of life,<note place="margin">Iohn 14, 6</note> becauſe they treate of Ieſus Chriſt, who is the life of life: for in him we liue, moue,<note place="margin">Actes 4, 12</note> &amp; haue our being. And not only Peter ſaith:<note place="margin">Acts 10, 43</note> 
                  <hi>Non eſt ſalus in vllo alio,</hi> but <hi>huic teſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes prophetae.</hi> To him doe all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets beare witneſſe, <hi>that through his name al that beleeue in him, ſhal receiue remiſſion of ſinnes.</hi> The wordes of the Goſpell are called the wordes of life alſo, becauſe the ſubiect of the goſpel is to beget ſoules to euerlaſting life: as our Sauiour himſelfe ſaieth,<note place="margin">Iohn 20, 31</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe things were written that you might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and in beleeuing yee might haue life through Chriſts name.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:19805:12"/>
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>So when they heard it, they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the temple early in the morning and taught.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>This ſequele ſheweth how faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the Apoſtles did execute the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels commandement; Firſt they doe heare it,<note place="margin">Ezec. 33, 7</note> then they teach it: like that rule of God to <hi>Ezechiel, Sonne of man thou ſhalt heare the word at my mouth, and thou ſhalt giue the people warning from me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4, 11</note> Or that of S. <hi>Peter, If anie man miniſter, let him do it as of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie that God ministreth to him.</hi> For our ſauiour ſaith,<note place="margin">Math. 13.52</note> 
                  <hi>Euery Scribe learned in the kingdome of God, is like a good houſholder that bringeth out of his trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, things both new and old.</hi> Thus the meanes are directed to the ende, as Moſes receiued the lawe, to deliuer it to the people. The eare to heare, and the eie to ſee, the Lorde hath made them both ſaith the Wiſe man.<note place="margin">Prou. 20, 12</note> 
                  <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> teacheth vs both the vſe and the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19805:12"/>
author of our ſenſes: by both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he affirmeth that we are gods factors vpon earth, and that the gifts of God are talents committed to vs, to trade them ouer in our life, to the honor of the right owner of them.<note place="margin">Luke 4, 16</note> The Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Luke ſaith, that when our Lord came into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynagogue of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> (according to his cuſtome) hee gaue them a ſermon: And ſo doeth hee ſaie likewiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Luke 24, 53</note> that they were vſuallie conuerſing in the Temple, in the time of their libertie, and novve alſo after their impriſonment. This is one great comfort to the man of god, that howſoeuer men may be bounde for the worde of God,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2, 9</note> yet the worde of God it ſelfe is not bound.</p>
               <p>And let them further vnderſtande, that as Gods iudgments are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a great deep,<note place="margin">Pſal. 36, 6</note> ſo he wil not make it known vnto vs, why he ſuffereth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ride ouer our heads, but only thus far forth, that we may finde him moſt
<pb facs="tcp:19805:13"/>
helpefull, when we feele our ſelues to be moſt helpleſſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37, 25</note> and ſay like Dauid, <hi>I neuer ſawe the righteous forſaken.</hi> And thereby learne, that bicauſe God is mercifull, therefore he ought to be feared more then men, who are for the moſt part cruell.</p>
               <p>When it is ſaid, that the Apoſtles <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred earlie into the temple and taught.</hi> This is ſpoken for the imitation of their ſucceſſors: for euen as the ſun imparteth his light vnto the moone and ſtarres, ſo theſe moouing candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks bee not put vnder a buſhell, but ſet in an open place, to inlighten all that are in Gods houſe.<note place="margin">Iohn 5.35</note> According as the ſcripture ſaith of S. Iohn, <hi>That hee was a burning and a ſhining light:</hi> meaning that he conſumed himſelfe to giue light to other. In ſome place the miniſter earlie is vp, but the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple neuer the nearer: yet theſe apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles enter betimes into the temple, &amp; doe teach. Ieſus Chriſt is called the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19805:13"/>
day ſpring, or the breake of the daie.<note place="margin">Luke 1, 78</note> And ſo is his worde comparable to the ſtar that conducted the wiſe men vnto him.<note place="margin">Math. 2, 9</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 3, 1</note> The church wanted this light in Salomons time,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 3, 1</note> but ſpecially in the daies of <hi>Samuel.</hi> Miſerable is their ſtate who liue in ignorance, for the blinde eateth many a flie, as the Phariſies are ſaide to ſwallowe whole Camels.<note place="margin">Mat. 23, 24</note> Wherfore we are very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py men,<note place="margin">2 Titus 21</note> to whome the <hi>grace of GOD hath appeared.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>And taught.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>Bicauſe the word of God hath parted the whole worlde into a vineyarde of worke, and a market place of Idlenes,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.1, 3</note> and God hath aſwell forbid loytering as commanded labouring:<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3, 10</note> therefore he taketh men from Idlenes,<note place="margin">Math. 20, 7</note> and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them to their occupation, to teach that they onely are worthie of their calling which walke according to the ſame: as Eſay ſaide,<note place="margin">Eſay 50, 4</note> 
                  <hi>The Lorde hath giuen me a tongue of the learned,
<pb facs="tcp:19805:14"/>
that I ſhuld kno how to miniſter a word in due ſeaſon to him that is weary.</hi> And as Paule commanded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which wil drinke wine, ſhould help to plant the vine,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9</note> and him that liueth of the altar, to miniſter at the altar: and him that wil eate the milke, to feede the flock. I alledge not this, as though I thoght them to bee ignorant of this point of Diſcipline, to whom it ſpecially per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, but as knowing that they which ſhoulde ſpeciallie remember it, doe chiefely forgette it.</p>
               <p>There is one leſſon in the ſcripture that manie one in the miniſterie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth one halfe of it, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth the other halfe: and it vvas ſpoken by our Sauiour to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, immediatly after that he heard of the death of Iohn the Baptiſt. The wordes are <hi>Come aſide,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 6, 31</note> 
                  <hi>and reſte a while.</hi> Euery one vpon the leaſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, very readily commeth apart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> labor to loiter, and is preſt to take his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19805:14"/>
reſt: but they either forget that it is ſaid, <hi>Reſt a while,</hi> or elſe think a whole yeares eaſe to be but a while. But they ſhould reſt as Chriſt did,<note place="margin">Iohn 4, 6</note> ſitting vpon Iacobs well: viz. vntill they are refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,<note place="margin">Iohn 5, 17</note> and then to it againe by Chriſts example: <hi>for my father worketh hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto and I worke,</hi> ſaith hee. And by Iacobs ſleeping in the land of <hi>Haran:</hi> for he laide a ſtone vnder his head, in ſteed of a ſoft pillow,<note place="margin">Gen. 28, 11</note> &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning was packing on toward <hi>Bethel:</hi> teaching men to meaſure their eaſe, as well as their paines. So God allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth intermiſſion, for hee will haue line after line,<note place="margin">Eſay 28, 10</note> and precept after pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, but alloweth no Idleneſſe: and therefore hee ſaide to thoſe loyterers in the market place:<note place="margin">Math. 20, 6</note> 
                  <hi>Why ſtande yee idle?</hi> And therefore Paule calleth the Office of a biſhop a good worke,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3, 1</note> in that they taught <hi>the people.</hi> It ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as much to our folkes condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation, as for their peoples commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,
<pb facs="tcp:19805:15"/>
euen as Chriſt ſaieth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Sabaes</hi> comming to hear Salomons wiſdom ſhall condemn the Iewes in the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment daye.<note place="margin">Math. 12, 42</note> Our Sauiour hath alſo taught, what is the cauſe of our ſlow aſſemblies,<note place="margin">Luke 12, 34</note> when he telleth that mens harts are only there, where their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is. But yet euen in pollicie, wee know that wiſe marchants wil traffike into diuers countries, yea and ſende their chiefeſt wares into thoſe partes where there is like to be longeſt peace and ſafeſt trauaile: Why then ſhould not the ſpirituall marchant laye vppe treaſure in heauen, where is all good hope of endles happines, ſeeing the ſcripture ſaith (and therefore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth ſaieth) <hi>that there theeues cannot break through and ſteale,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 6, 19 20</note> &amp; by ſtealing make vs bankerout of euerlaſting bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>Then the chiefe prieſt came, &amp; they that were with him, and called the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell together, and all the Elders of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19805:15"/>
children of Iſrael, and ſent to the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to cauſe them to be brought.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>If wee regard the outward perſons in this aſſemblie, it may ſeeme that it was very lawful: but if we conſider the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their comming togither, we ſhall finde it moſt vngodlie: for it is a consu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mation of king Dauids pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pheſie,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 2, 2</note> vvho ſaide that mightie men ſhould aſſemble themſelues againſte the Lord, and his annointed, which is his Chriſt. The ſcripture giueth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of diuers aſſemblies, whereof ſome haue come together for good endes, and ſome haue muſtered for bad intents. The godly aſſemblies are expreſſed in that of Cornelius and his companye,<note place="margin">Acts. 10.33</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2, 1</note> and in that cloude of witneſſes, the apoſtles aſſemble at Ieruſalem, being al together with one accord, in one place. Vnhallowed aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, are ſuch as thoſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of Numbers, when <hi>Korah Leuies</hi> ſon,<note place="margin">Num. 16, 1</note> conſpired with <hi>Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19805:16"/>
the ſonnes of <hi>Eliab,</hi> againſt Moſes and Aaron.<note place="margin">Numb. 14, 2</note> And when the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of Iſraell aſſembled againſte theſe two at another time. Fiue kings againſte Captaine Ioſuah,<note place="margin">Ioſua 10</note> and theſe counſellers at Ieruſalem againſt the men of God. Then out of this place wee are aduertiſed, howe little hope there is of concluding any good, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aſſemblie hath neither feare nor knowledge of God. For as menne in chiefeſt ſeats do commit the chiefeſt ſinnes, ſo may wee thinke that Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monwealth to bee in the afternoone of her age, viz. in a declining ſtate where iudgement is committed vnto ſuch, as ſhould rather bee iudged. It is neither heere nor there,<note place="margin">Pſal. 58, 1</note> vvhoe are aſſembled, except their mindes are ſette vppon righteouſneſſe, to iudge the thinge that is equall. The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the aſſemblie prooueth not the goodneſſe of it, for then the fiue kinges hadde foyled Ioſuah,<note place="margin">Ioſuah 10</note> and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19805:16"/>
Councell of Ieruſalem muſte needes haue ſwallovved vppe theſe ſillie A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. But it is true, that thorough Gods permiſſion, the mightie often times ſurpriſe the meaner ſort: and that made the Philoſopher laughe in his ſleeue, to ſee great theeues leade little theeues to priſon. Chriſt muſte be crucified to the vvorlds end,<note place="margin">Amos 2.13</note> euen as cartes are preſſed with ſheaues ſo long as there is any harueſt. Aske the ſhower of the Saints bloud els,<note place="margin">Mat. 23, 35</note> which began with the bloud of <hi>Abell,</hi> and helde on to the bloud of <hi>Zacharias</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Barachias.</hi> Aske the riuer of bloud, which the enemies of Gods truth haue ſhed in warre. And aske the vvorde of trueth,<note place="margin">Matth. 2, 16</note> howe much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud hypocriſie hath broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and it will aunſwere you like Saule:<note place="margin">Act 22, 4</note> 
                  <hi>I perſecuted this way vnto the death, &amp;c.</hi> Howbeit, whenſoeuer (thorough GODS grace) we change our nature, hee alſo vouchſafeth vs
<pb facs="tcp:19805:17"/>
a new name, as he did turne <hi>Saule</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Paule, Abram</hi> into <hi>Abraham,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iacob</hi> into Iſraell. But that which is here ſaid, <hi>That the chiefe prieſt came and they that were with him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">❀</note> giueth vs warning, how we come in companie with euill aſſociates, like Peter vvith the high prieſts ſeruants.<note place="margin">Luke 22, 55</note> But ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie that we conſent not to their euils, as acceſſaries thereto, as <hi>Saule</hi> did to <hi>Stephens</hi> death,<note place="margin">Acts 8, 1 Luke 22, 4</note> and <hi>Iudas</hi> to that trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon againſt Chriſts perſon, and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> with <hi>Pilate</hi> to his arraignment.<note place="margin">Luke 23, 12</note> If we haue intent to doe it, it is euen as bad as if we had done it. Chriſt ſayth, that whoe ſo luſteth after a woman hath ſinned in his hart. And hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Phariſies murderers,<note place="margin">Iohn 8, 44</note> when they only intended his death (&amp; had not crucified him) becauſe although their power coulde not performe his death aſſoone as they would, yet their will was not wanting: and ſo are all they no leſſe guiltie of euill, who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie
<pb facs="tcp:19805:17"/>
giue conſent to it, although they act it not in their owne perſons. When olde Iacob bleſſed his ſonnes he ſaide of <hi>Simeon</hi> &amp; <hi>Leuie:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49, 6 Acts. 8, 1</note> 
                  <hi>Into their counſel come not my ſoule.</hi> Paule caſt not one ſtone at <hi>Stephen:</hi> but yet in conſenting to his death, he ſinned as greeuouſly. <hi>Ahab</hi> ſtoned not <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both,</hi> but yet hee conſented thereto, and ſealed the proclamation of his death, which was as bad. So the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters made the Croſſe, the Ievves receiued it, <hi>Simon</hi> bare it, but Chriſt was crucified vppon it, and ſo they made an end of him, and them. <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis magni malis, ſunt obnoxii</hi> great men do offend in great matters. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore <hi>be wiſe O Kinges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2, 10</note> and <hi>learned yee iudges of the earth,</hi> ſaith the wiſe kings father. God refuſeth zeale without knovvledge, al your good intents are but as blinde men, that will venter to goe without a guide.<note place="margin">Rom. 10, 2</note> If you ſet good meaning before knowledge; you ſet
<pb facs="tcp:19805:18"/>
the blinde to lead the ſeeing, or the cart to dravv the horſe. Theſe magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates conſult againe and againe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the meſſengers of GOD, for wickednes laboureth the downfall of goodneſſe, as the Ievves hacked at the greene tree.<note place="margin">Luke 23, 31</note> The ſcripture auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, that a mannes death may bee ſought ſixe waies. Firſt by deceiuing him in a caſe concerning his life, as the diuel did <hi>Adam.</hi> Secondly, by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering violence to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Gen. 3, 1</note> as <hi>Saule</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> did. Thirdly, by denying nouriſhment, to hold life and ſoule to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether, as the rich man did to <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus.</hi> 4. By forbearing to comfort the weake, as the Leuite did not regarde the wounded <hi>Samaritane.</hi> 5. By com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manding, as <hi>Ieſabel</hi> to put <hi>Naboth</hi> to death for his Vineyard. And laſtly, by giuing counſell, as <hi>Herodias</hi> daughter being aduiſed by her mother, begged Iohn the Baptiſtes head: and as the high prieſt and Saduces held a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19805:18"/>
againſt the Apoſtles. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe ſaieth, that the fierceſt lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings do beat vpon the loftieſt tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. And the author to the Hebrues,<note place="margin">Heb. 1, 7 Actes 5, 19</note> 
                  <hi>That God maketh his Angels ſpirites:</hi> as is prooued by the ſpirituall deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of theſe men of god, by the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of God. And further, that <hi>God maketh his miniſters a flame of fire,</hi> and it is dangerous to deale with fire: Yet theſe magiſtrates muſter togither, as to the putting out of a daungerous fire: and are as much troubled in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the truth,<note place="margin">Math. 2.3</note> as <hi>Herod</hi> was to hear of Chriſtes kingdome and all Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem with him. Wel, they were decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: for this fire is none other but that which was figured in the Leuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal law, and muſt burne vnquenched.<note place="margin">Leuit. 6, 13</note> For ſo Chriſt ſaith:<note place="margin">Luke 12, 49</note> I am come to ſet fire on the earth, and what is my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, but that it ſhould burne. As the emptieſt veſſels make the loudeſt lum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bring, ſo the moſt irreligious are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:19805:19"/>
moſt officious: but as it is errour to affirme an vntruth, and hereſie to vphold it: ſo is it cruelty to impriſon without iuſt cauſe, and tyrannie to proſecute that ſute: and as Thornes were the matter whereof Chriſtes crowne was platted,<note place="margin">Math. 23, 29</note> ſo affliction is the crowne wherevvith our mother the church honoreth vs her children. <hi>Spina Chriſti corona noſtri,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cant. 3, 11</note> Chriſtes thorne is our Crowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Text. <q>
                     <hi>And ſent to the priſon, to cauſe them to be brought, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </q>
               </head>
               <p>The voice which ſtroke <hi>Saule</hi> to, the ground,<note place="margin">Acts. 9, 3, 1</note> came not vntill hee vvas neere to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> where hee meant to make hauocke of the church. And the wordes were,<note place="margin">verſe 4, 5</note> 
                  <hi>Saule, Saule, whie perſecuteſt thou me, &amp;c.</hi> Firſt to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that there is no more honourable victorie, then to vanquiſh when men are in the very pitch of their purpoſe: and ſecondly, to ſignifie how bootles that battaile is, that is waged againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19805:19"/>
God. <hi>Quid me perſequeris?</hi> Why per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecuteſt thou me? Is as much as God had ſaide: That there is no reaſon to be angry with God, the author of our good. <hi>It is hard for thee to kick againſt the prickes:</hi> ſignifieth, the meere follie of ſuch, as enterpriſe ſo booteleſſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, as doe hurt themſelues more then harme them whom they reſiſt. For he that kicketh againſt a pricke, hurteth himſelfe, and not the goade: Like the mad man that did cut him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with flintes.<note place="margin">Exo. 14, 27</note> While Pharao pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth Iſrael, he periſheth. <hi>Abſolon</hi> hunting after his father,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18, 9</note> is hanged vp in an Oake. <hi>Arams</hi> hoaſt labouring to get <hi>Eliſha</hi> the prophet, are led into <hi>Samaria</hi> by <hi>Eliſha</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">2 Reg. 6.</note> where (of al the places of the world) they would not be.<note place="margin">Prou. 21, 30</note> There is no conſulting againſt God, ſaith the vviſe man, for he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the wiſe in his owne witte. Therefore ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 26, 27</note> 
                  <hi>He that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a pit ſhal fall therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19805:20"/>
                  <note place="margin">1 Eſd. 14, 16</note>Wee ſee, that it is true that <hi>Eſdras</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>That the world will increaſe in euil as it groweth in age.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Suſan. 52</note> Like the Iudge to whom <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid: <hi>So thou that art olde in euil.</hi> The councell had firſt impriſoned theſe Apoſtles, and then they proceede to iudge them, that they may growe from one wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes into another.<note place="margin">Gen. 19, 33</note> Like <hi>Antiochus</hi> Elephants,<note place="margin">Maca. 6, 34</note> that at the ſight of bloud were mooued to ſeeke bloud: Or as <hi>Herod,</hi> who ſeeing that the death of <hi>Iames</hi> delighted the Iewes, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſerue Peter ſo to: Or like the Foxes,<note place="margin">Acts 12, 3</note> which for deſire of bloud, kill more carcaſes then they can deuour. The ſcripture mentioneth three <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods,</hi> and they were al murderers. For the firſt killed the infantes at the birth of Chriſt, the ſecond (in his cups) beheaded Iohn the Baptiſt, and the third (to curry fauour with the Iewes) ſlue Iames with the ſword, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the death of Peter to, but God
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19805:20"/>
did preuent him therein, as hee did theſe in their purpoſe. There bee too many ſuch <hi>Herods,</hi> who hadde rather pleaſure men by committing euil, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleaſe God by doing good.</p>
               <p>I ſpeake it not to declaime againſt impiety, for that (I feare) were boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, but to reclaime al to pitty. God grant it may not bee fruitleſſe. Wee haue many demonſtrations of Gods ſnaky pace to reuenge, vvho ſuffereth his owne to be (as Dauid ſaieth) euill intreated of Tyrantes, and yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God that threw downe the Angels when they abuſed their good ſtate,<note place="margin">Iude 6</note> as ſaint <hi>Iude</hi> witneſſeth, is patient with men, whetting his ſword as threatning to ſtrike vs, and bending his bow,<note place="margin">Pſal. 64.7</note> as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to ſhoote at vs with a very ſwift arrow, ſo that we ſhalbe woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if we returne not in time. He ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Saule</hi> while hee is not contented to perſecute at Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Acts. 9.1</note> but procee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth to Damaſcus too. This, I ſaie,
<pb facs="tcp:19805:21"/>
God ſeeth, &amp; yet he ſuffereth it. But a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſcripture ſaith of <hi>Saule,</hi> firſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauit veſtes,</hi> he held their clothes who were the tormentors, meaning that hee woulde playe ſmall game, rather then want a part in ſuch actions. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlie, that hee conſented to Stee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uens death: ſignifying, that then hee came to ſinne in a ſecond degree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Saintes: and thirdlie, that he made hauocke of the Church of God.<note place="margin">Acts 9, 4</note> Thus ſhewing how hee ſinned by degrees. So when God called him, he fell downe in haſt,<note place="margin">Luke 19, 6</note> as <hi>Zacheus</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted downe from the wild Figge tree.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
